A Guide to the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historic Properties Collection, 1989-2006
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historic Properties Collection, 1989-2006
Special Collections, James Madison University
5016
2.8 linear feet; three Hollinger boxes and one oversized box, 18" x 23" x 3"
The collection contains National Register of Historic Places nomination forms for properties in the vicinity of Rockingham County and the City of Harrisonburg created by students in James Madison University's Historic Preservation class, 1989-2006; includes supporting documents: maps, floor plans and images used to supplement the nomination forms.
Students in Mr. Darryl Nash's Historic Preservation class, HIST 463/693, ARTH 493, James Madison University.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Received from Mr. Darryl Nash in June 2006.
Accruals
May receive regular additions of material
Custodial History
Provenance: The Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historic Properties Collection came into existence in 1989 when HIST 493/693 was first offered at James Madison University. Taught by Dr. Darryl Nash since its inception, the purpose of the course was to teach students historic preservation techniques, while providing a hands on project solidifying those objectives taught in class. At the end of term, students were expected to complete a Nomination form ready for submittal to the Department of Historic Places. Mr. Nash had retained a sizeable collection of student projects, and donated them to Special Collections in the Fall of 2006.
Historical Information
Properties represented in the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historic Properties Collection provides lasting documentation of significant properties in the Harrisonburg-Rockingham County area. The unique architecture and historical significance of these properties provided the foundation for consideration for nomination of the National Register of Historic Places.
Architectural styles in Rockingham County and the City of Harrisonburg differ from eastern Virginia largely due to early settlement patterns. Rockingham County was formally established in 1777 from Augusta and Orange counties. The physical geography of Rockingham County, located west of the Blue Ridge Mountains, deterred most settlers on the eastern coast from crossing the mountains to explore western Virginia. The emigrants of Rockingham County thus hearkened from Northern states, such as Pennsylvania and Maryland, bringing with them architectural styles from their Germanic, Swiss, and Scots-Irish heritage.
There were two distinct periods of development in America, both of which influenced architectural choices in Rockingham County and Harrisonburg; the Antebellum period from 1830-1860 and the Reconstruction and Growth period from 1865 to 1917. The dominating styles in Rockingham County ranged from 19th century Colonial (as seen in the Mannheim House,) 19th century Georgian (as seen in the Emanuel Roller House and the Contentment House,) 19th century Federal (as seen in the Jacob Yount House,) to 20th century Modern. Transitional styles include the Queen Anne Style, Gothic and Greek Revival, Italianate, and Colonial Revival. All of these distinct styles were modified to reflect local traditions and customs. This change of style, due to local materials, craftsmen, and traditions, is known as vernacular style. All of the houses in this collection represent some form of vernacular styles, while reflecting the national architecture as well.
Some of the more notable properties in the collection include:
The Thomas Harrison House: The historical context of the Thomas Harrison House is vital to the Harrisonburg community as it was the home of its founder, Thomas Harrison. The house represents the first permanent structure of the area, as well as one of the only surviving vernacular stone structures. This circa 1750 house reflects the 18th century vernacular style to its fullest extent. The house, built of limestone rubble, is a one and half story single pile structure over a raised basement with an attic. The basement was built over a spring, which is characteristic of many early Rockingham County houses.
Mannheim: This property serves as an example of 18th century farm life and the institution of slavery, which was not widespread in Rockingham County as in central and eastern Virginia. Architecturally, the Mannheim house represents the Germanic influence. Built in 1750 with a massive central chimney, this two story house displays fine Germanic craftsmanship. The property also includes several examples of outbuildings, including a springhouse, icehouse, and slave quarters.
Contentment: The historical context of Contentment has both political and social elements. Members of the Grattan family, the original builders of the house, served in the Virginia House of Delegates. In 1864, the land surrounding Contentment was used during the Civil War as Confederate troops organized these prior to the Battle of Piedmont. Socially, the Grattan family represents one of the most prominent Scots-Irish families in Rockingham County, as the family has resided in Contentment since 1761 and helped support Revolutionary War efforts. The Contentment House is a large, two-story Georgian style farmhouse built in 1823. With the traditional pattern of two windows aside a central door, a second story aligned with the same layout, and fireplaces on the gable end, the house remains relatively unchanged.
John Paul House: This property, as its name suggests, is significant largely due to the significance of its inhabitants. The Paul family boasts two federal judges and one state judge. Most prominent was Peter Paul, Jr. who was appointed Justice of the Peace in 1855. The John Paul House, also known as the Ottobine Farm, is representative of the changing architectural styles of the nineteenth century as it reflects both Late Victorian Gothic style and Greek Revival portico to match the family's growing prosperity in Harrisonburg.
Peale House: Jonathan Peale, the owner, was a wealthy farmer and prominent citizen in early Harrisonburg history. However, its historical significance stems from its association with General Thomas Stonewall Jackson, who was said to have set up base at the Peale House prior to the Battle of Cross Keys and Port Republic. The Peale house is a unique example of Gothic Revival architectural style incorporated with vernacular style built in the 1840s. Constructed of brick, the house boasts Doric columns supporting a two story portico on the front and two story columns supporting the back porches; these features are reminiscent of ancient Greek temples hence the style name.
Scope and Content
The Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historic Properties Collection consists of 2.8 linear feet of material, c. 1989 to 2006. The collection was generated by students in Mr. Darryl Nash's Historic Preservation Class (HIST 493,693, ARTH 493) at James Madison University. The only exception to this is the Graves Chapel Property which was completed by Mr. Nash himself. The collection primarily contains National Register Nomination Forms and supporting material for potential property candidates for the National Register of Historic places in Harrisonburg and Rockingham County, supported by a wide array of documents and images relating to each property. It is arranged chronologically by date generated, then alphabetically by property with the following subseries: Forms, Supporting Documents, Images, and Oversized. For more a more detailed list for each property please see itemized contents list.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically by the date the project was completed, then alphabetically. Within project folders, documents are arranged according to the following series: Forms, Supporting Documents and Images. For more a more detailed list for each property please see itemized contents list. Asterisks before a project title in the finding aid indicate that there are materials in the oversized series relating to that project.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Massey, James C. Shirley et. al. Shenandoah County Historic resources survey: survey report. Richmond, VA: The Virginia Department of Historic Resources, 1995.
National Register of Historic Places. SED/JJ. 2 February 2007. http://www.cr.nps.gov/nr, National Park Service.
Suter, Scott H. and Cheryl Lyon. Harrisonburg. Chicago: Arcadia, 2003.
Suter, Scott H. and Cheryl Lyon. Places, Faces, and Traces: Historical Photographs of Harrisonburg and Rockingham County. Dayton, VA: Silver Lake Mill, 2005.
Terrell, Isaac Long. Old Houses in Rockingham County, 1750-1850. Verona, VA: McClure Printing Company, 1970.
Related Material
See also the Margaret Grattan Weaver collection, SC# 2030
Separated Material
Photocopied and/or duplicated material was separated from the collection. Original wallpaper samples from the Kiser-Roller House (1993) and the Liskey House (1995) were scanned and discarded. Two irregularly sized floor plans for the Lincoln-Pennybacker House (1989) had been pieced with tape, and thus were scanned and discarded. Images for the O.C. Sterling House (1989) had been pasted on mat board, which were scanned.
Contents List (Box:Folder)
- Itemized Contents List
- Undated
  - Lethe Property (1:1)
- 1989
  - *Herringford (1:2)
  - Lincoln-Pennybacker House, Hand drafted floor plans, 4 pp, 2 scanned: Image 1(1.54mb) Image 2(1.5mb) (1:3)
  - Maplewood: John Hopkins House (1:4)
  - O.C. Sterling House, Link to images 1-3 (940kb), Link to images 4-7(.98mb) (1:5)
  - Thomas Harrison House (1:6)
- 1991
  - *Rockingham Motor Company (1:7)
  - *Twin Maples (1:8)
- 1993
  - John Roller, Sr. (1:9)
  - Kiser-Roller House, Scans of plaster and wallpaper samples from parlor room: 1 (1.38mb) 2 (1.42mb) 3 (1.29mb) 4 (1.42mb) 5 (2.07mb) 6 (962kb) 7 (625kb) (1:10)
  - Seller's House (1:11)
  - *Jacob Yount House (1:12)
- 1994
  - *Idlewood Farm (1:13)
  - Long's Chapel (Zenda) (1:14)
- 1995
  - *Barrybuck House (1:15)
  - Liskey Buildings (See also Liskey Farm, 2005), Link to wallpaper sample(2mb) (1:16)
- 1996
  - Isaac Hardesty House (1:17)
  - Peale House (2:1)
- 1997
  - *Contentment (2:2)
  - Mannheim (2:3)
- 1998
  - First National Bank (2:4)
  - Graves Chapel (2:5)
- 1999
  - Greenland Home (1:6)
  - Shoe Factory (2:7-8)
  - Tide Spring (2:9)
- 2000
  - Breneman's Mill (see also 2003) (2:10)
  - Paul House (2:11-12)
  - Saufley-Frysinger House (2:13)
  - Train Depot and Gas Stations (2:14)
- 2001
  - Hardesty-Higgins House Committee (2:15)
  - Pence Farm/Spring (2:16)
  - Whitmore House (2:17)
- 2002
  - Greenmount Farm (3:1-2)
- 2003
  - Breneman's Mill (see also 2000) (3:3)
  - *Burkeholder-Myers House (3:4)
  - *Fawley Homeplace (3:5)
- 2004
  - *Blosser House (3:6-7)
  - *Shepherd of the Valley Lutheran Church Dayton Chapel (3:8)
  - Showalter (3:9)
- 2005
  - *Liskey Farm (see also Liskey Buildings, 1995) (3:10)
- 2006
  - *Craney Island (3:11)
  - Winston-Liskey House Project (3:12)
- Oversized
  - Blosser House, 2004, hand drafted floor plans [18"x24", 3pp]
  - Burkeholder-Myers House, 2003, hand drafted floor plans [18"x24"]
  - Contentment, 1997, hand drafted floor plans [17"x22", 3pp]
  - Craney Island, 2006, hand drafted floor plans [18"x24", 4 pp]
  - Fawley Homeplace, 2003, hand drafted floor plans [18"x24"]
  - Herringford, 1989, hand drafted floor plans [16"x19", 3pp]
  - Idlewood Farm, 1994: Hand drafted floor plans [18"x24", 5pp] and Land Survey circa 1989 [11"x17"]
  - Liskey Buildings, 1995, hand drafted floor plans [18"x24", 9pp]
  - Liskey Farm, 2005, hand drafted floor plans [18"x24", 4pp]
  - Rockingham Motor Company, 1991, blueprints [24"x36", 3pp]
  - Shepherd of the Valley Lutheran Church Dayton Chapel 2004, blueprints [26 1/2"x31 1/2"]
  - Showalter, 2004, hand drafted floor plans [24"x36"]